Guide to the Henry Scholey Saunders Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Henry Scholey Saunders papers,
1884-1951
[Bulk Dates: 1911-1947]
Saunders, Henry Scholey, 1864-1951.
.21 linear ft. (1/2 document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1111
4079300
Henry Scholey Saunders’ collection is comprised of letters, photographs, newspaper clippings, and hand painted watercolor greeting cards. In addition, the collection contains family files, bibliographies of Walt Whitman’s works, and typewritten excerpts of Walt Whitman’s published poems.
Biographical Note
Henry Scholey Saunders was born in 1864 in London, Canada. He married Georgina Helen Taylor on October 10, 1887 and they settled in Toronto for the rest of their lives. They had two children, a son, Harry Ernest, and a daughter, Ruth Mercer, who died at the age of two.
Saunders was a Toronto cellist, collector, bibliographer, and independent Walt Whitman enthusiast. He was a self-taught bookbinder, painter and typesetter, skills he used to write and produce his own books on Whitman's poems in limited quantities, which he gave to friends and kept for his own Whitman collection. His method of publishing was unique: he typed, bound, and carefully catalogued these books by hand. He ultimately sold his collection to Brown University in 1932. His only published work was Parodies on Whitman (1923).
Saunders died on October 25, 1951 at the age of eighty-eight.
Scope and Content
The Saunders collection consists primarily of correspondence (letters and greeting cards) to friends and business clients, and materials related to Whitman - handwritten bibliographies, reprints of poems on greeting cards, notes, articles, photographs and programs.
There are also family files consisting of newspaper clippings and personal papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1921-1947
Series II: Family Files, 1923-1951
Series III: Collection on Walt Whitman, 1884-1951
Series IV: Greeting Cards, 1940-1947
Subjects
Brown University--Library--Manuscript Collections; Brown University--Library--Special Collections; Saunders, Henry Scholey, 1864-1951.; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892.; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Appreciation; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Appreciation--United States; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Bibliography; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Bibliography--Catalog; Drawings.; Greeting cards.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Sprague, Mrs. Frank J. Gift 1952 M-52
Selected Related Material-- Other Repositories
Henry Scholey Saunders' Collection of Walt Whitman, 1877-1950, John Hay Library, Brown University.
Henry Scholey Saunders' Collection of Walt Whitman Papers, 1887-1923, Library of Congress.
Henry Scholey Saunders Vertical File Manuscript, 1945-, Morris Library, Southern Illinois University.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1921 - 1947
  This series consists primarily of letters written to Mrs. Frank J. Sprague, a close friend of Saunders and to whom he gave copies of his Whitman books. Other letters were to business clients.
  - Letter to Mr. F.C. Thwing, 1930 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Mrs. Frank J. Sprague, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters with Mr. Jefferson Winter, 1921 April-October (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Family Files, 1923-1951
  Materials in this series include newspaper clippings such as an obituary written by Mrs. Frank J. Sprague in the Long-Islander newspaper in 1951, a typed document about the Saunders’ Reunion Fund and family photographs.
  - Photographs, 1930-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1937-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter from Charles Saunders, 1923 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Genealogy Chart, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III: Collection on Walt Whitman, 1884-1951
  Much of the items in this series are typed Whitman’s poems (excerpts and complete) by other people, bibliographies, notes and articles about Whitman. There are also photographs of Whitman, his home, and Saunders’ personal bound book collection.
  - Photographs of Whitman and Other Subjects, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Printed Materials, 1884-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notes and Articles, 1912-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Walt Whitman Fellowship Programs, Canadian Branch, 1916-1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed Walt Whitman’s Poems on Cards, 1911-1920 (Box 1)
- Series IV: Greeting Cards, 1940-1947
  This series contains hand painted watercolor greeting cards from Saunders to Mrs. Frank J. Sprague.
  - Hand-painted Watercolor Greeting Cards, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)